<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE content
[
<!--======================================== modify but don't delete ========================================-->
 <!ENTITY base "./">
 <!ENTITY title	"Business ethics in the face of monopolistic threats">
 <!ENTITY this "ethics.html">
 <!ENTITY maintainer "&lt;a href=&quot;http://norbert.ch/&quot;&gt;Norbert Bollow&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:nb@cisto.com&quot;&gt;&_lt_;nb@cisto.com&_gt_;&lt;/a&gt;">
 <!ENTITY modtime "Thu March 13, 2003">
<!--======================================== modify but don't delete ========================================-->

<!--======================================== add custom entities here ========================================-->
<!--======================================== add custom entities here ========================================-->

<!--======================================== declared here, defined elsewhere ========================================-->

 <!-- First block: "Homepage" + Information that sells DotGNU to developers -->
 <!ENTITY nav.functionality "">
 <!ENTITY nav.freedom "">
 <!ENTITY nav.web_services "">
 <!ENTITY nav.auth "">
 <!ENTITY nav.innovation "">
 <!ENTITY nav.stereo "">
 <!ENTITY nav.acronyms "">
 <!ENTITY nav.testimonials "">
 <!ENTITY nav.win "">

 <!-- Second block: "Useful DotGNU Software" - Let the code talk -->
 <!ENTITY nav.phpgw "">
 <!ENTITY nav.pnet "">
 <!ENTITY nav.snapshots "">
 <!ENTITY nav.downloads "">
 <!ENTITY nav.debs "">

 <!-- Third block: DotGNU Developers Community -->
 <!ENTITY nav.lists "">
 <!ENTITY nav.wiki "">
 <!ENTITY nav.irc "">
 <!ENTITY nav.join "">

<!-- Fourth block: Advocacy -->
 <!ENTITY nav.advocacy "">
 <!ENTITY nav.posters "">

<!-- Fifth block: Misc Information -->
 <!ENTITY nav.arch "">
 <!ENTITY nav.projects "">
 <!ENTITY nav.pnet.lib.status "">
 <!ENTITY nav.pnet.lib.docs "">
 <!ENTITY nav.patent "">

 <!ENTITY misc.gnu "">
 <!ENTITY misc.dotgnu "">
 <!ENTITY _lt_ "">
 <!ENTITY _gt_ "">
 <!ENTITY _quot_ "">
 <!ENTITY _apos_ "">
 <!ENTITY _amp_ "">
 <!ENTITY nbsp "">
 <!ENTITY copy "">
 <!ENTITY root "">
<!--======================================== declared here, defined elsewhere ========================================-->

<!--======================================== don't touch this stuff ========================================-->
 <!ELEMENT ul (li)+>
 <!ELEMENT ol (li)+>
 <!ELEMENT dl (dt|dd)+>
 <!ELEMENT dt (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img)*>
 <!ELEMENT li (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img | ul | ol | dl)*>
 <!ELEMENT dd (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img | ul | ol | dl)*>
 <!ELEMENT blockquote (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img | ul | ol | dl)*><!--no nesting blockquotes-->
 <!ELEMENT pre (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a)*><!--no images in pre-->
 <!ELEMENT a (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | img)*><!--no nesting anchors-->
 <!ELEMENT content (#PCDATA | include | p | h1 | h2 | h3 | h4 | pre | blockquote)*><!--block elements only in top level-->
 <!ELEMENT p (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img)*>
 <!ELEMENT em (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img)*>
 <!ELEMENT strong (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img)*>
 <!ELEMENT code (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img)*>
 <!ELEMENT h1 (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img)*>
 <!ELEMENT h2 (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img)*>
 <!ELEMENT h3 (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img)*>
 <!ELEMENT h4 (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img)*>
 <!ELEMENT br EMPTY>
 <!ELEMENT img EMPTY>
 <!ELEMENT include EMPTY>
 <!ATTLIST a title CDATA #IMPLIED name NMTOKEN #IMPLIED href CDATA #IMPLIED>
 <!ATTLIST img src CDATA #REQUIRED alt CDATA #REQUIRED align (top|middle|bottom|left|right) #IMPLIED>
 <!ATTLIST include file CDATA #REQUIRED entry NMTOKEN #IMPLIED overwrite (true|false) #IMPLIED>
<!--======================================== don't touch this stuff ========================================-->
]>

<content>
<h1>
Business Ethics In The Face Of Monopolistic Threats
</h1>
<p>
In view of the increasing commercialization of the Free Software movement,
it has become important to clarify a matter of business ethics that is all
too often overlooked.
</p>
<p>
This has to do with monopolies.  Copyright law allows the authors of
computer programs to have, for a limited period of time, monopoly rights
to modifying and copying the program.  For the sake of illustration, let's
compare this monopoly to a monopoly of oranges:  Imagine that in the whole
world there was only one place where orange trees grow, and imagine
furthermore that I am the owner of that area.  Then I have a monopoly of
oranges.  Let's suppose that I am generous and put up a sign that says
"Everyone is welcome to come and pick oranges".  It won't take long before
some entrepreneurial people pick more oranges than they want to eat
themselves, and start a business of selling oranges.  As long as there are
still plenty of oranges for everyone who wants to pick oranges, I wouldn't
mind that.  Effectively, what the businesses are selling is the
<EM>convenience</EM> of being able to conveniently buy the oranges, without
bothering about the harvest and transportation of the oranges.
</p>
<p>
This situation is comparable to a market for software which can be freely
copied and redistributed, without any monopolies.
</p>
<p>
However, I would get very upset if someone came and harvested <EM>all</EM>
oranges in order to gain control of the market and sell the oranges
at a higher price.  That would be exploiting my generosity in a totally
unethical manner.   
</p>
<p>
In the same way, when I contribute to a Free Software project, then I
my contribution to be for everyone's benefit, and I do not want anyone
to turn it into a monopoly.  In fact the whole point of the Free Software
movement is to get rid of software monopolies.  (Proprietary software is
software which has an "owner" who has a monopoly through having the right to
decide who can see the source code, who may modify the program, and who may
copy it for purposes of further distribution.  Free Software is software
where every user has these rights.)
</p>
<p>
The Free Software community welcomes businesses to get involved.  We don't
mind when the involved companies derive a profit from their involvement
(why else would be profit-oriented company get involved) as long as these
companies fight together with us at least against the worst software
monopolies.
</p>
<p>
In the context of DotGNU project this means:
<ol>
<li>If you earn money through distributing an improved version of some
DotGNU software, we expect you to also contribute the improvements back
to the development project, for everyone's benefit.  While the GNU General
Public License does not require you to do this, we will feel that you have
exploited our generosity in an unethical manner if you don't do this.</li>
<li>With .NET, Microsoft has introduced some technologies (in particular
C#, IL, and a significant amount of class libraries) that present a dilemma
for the GNU project and for the Free Software movement in general, and also
for the Open Source movement:  On one hand, if these technologies are not
available on our operating systems, then we must fear that these Free/Open
operating systems would die the slow death of software that is not updated to
adapt it to the evolving needs of the users.  On the other hand, endorsing
these technologies, the specifications of which are effectively controlled by
Microsoft, Inc., has significant risks also.  There are strong indications that
from a business strategy perspective, these technologies were designed
specifically with the goal to unleash a destructive Hailstorm against
the Open Source movement which has become a serious threat for Microsoft's
monopolistic strategies.  When a Free Software or Open Source company generates
profits by simply playing along with Microsoft's plan, that is therefore like
a betrayal against the Free Software and Open Source community.  (On the
other hand, there is nothing wrong with earning money through DotGNU'ish
efforts to counter the threat of the .NET in which Microsoft Inc. wants to
catch us.)
</li>
<li>The DotGNU project holds that with .NET-related stuff, it is not acceptable
for a company to ask contributors to assign copyright so that the company "can
use a dual license like Mozilla does for commercial purposes."   The Mozilla
project is a community effort to contribute to Free Software which competes
against "Internet Explorer", a program that was (in the judgment of US courts
of law) promoted by means of an "illegal monopoly" .  For .NET-related stuff,
when a company aligns its commercial interests with those of Microsoft, then
that company has no moral justification for asking volunteer contributors to
similarly assign copyright.
</li>
</ol>
</p>
<h2>
 Your comments please...
</h2>
<p class="maincontent">
You are invited to add your comments concerning this
at <a href="http://wiki.dotgnu.org/WebsiteComments/ethics">the appropriate
page of the DotGNU Wiki</a>
</p>
</content>
