<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE content
[
<!--======================================== modify but don't delete ========================================-->
 <!ENTITY base "./">
 <!ENTITY title	"DotGNU Project">
 <!ENTITY this "index.html">
 <!ENTITY maintainer "&lt;a href=&quot;http://norbert.ch/&quot;&gt;Norbert Bollow&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:nb@cisto.com&quot;&gt;&_lt_;nb@cisto.com&_gt_;&lt;/a&gt;">
 <!ENTITY modtime "Fri Aug 09 19:59:50 UTC 2002">
<!--======================================== modify but don't delete ========================================-->

<!--======================================== add custom entities here ========================================-->
<!--======================================== add custom entities here ========================================-->

<!--======================================== declared here, defined elsewhere ========================================-->
 <!ENTITY nav.snapshots "">
 <!ENTITY nav.debs "">
 <!ENTITY nav.faq "">
 <!ENTITY nav.essays "">
 <!ENTITY nav.proposals "">
 <!ENTITY nav.patent "">
 <!ENTITY nav.projects "">
 <!ENTITY nav.proposals.active "">
 <!ENTITY nav.arch "">
 <!ENTITY nav.see "">
 <!ENTITY nav.phpgw "">
 <!ENTITY nav.pnet "">
 <!ENTITY nav.pnet.lib.status "">
 <!ENTITY nav.pnet.lib.docs "">
 <!ENTITY nav.web_services "">
 <!ENTITY nav.auth "">
 <!ENTITY nav.mail.lists "">
 <!ENTITY nav.mail.pipermail "">
 <!ENTITY nav.mail.announce "">
 <!ENTITY nav.mail.developers "">
 <!ENTITY nav.mail.auth "">
 <!ENTITY nav.mail.arch "">
 <!ENTITY nav.mail.biz "">
 <!ENTITY nav.mail.website "">
 <!ENTITY misc.freedev "">
 <!ENTITY misc.gnu "">
 <!ENTITY misc.dotgnu "">
 <!ENTITY mail.gnu "">
 <!ENTITY mail.dotgnu "">
 <!ENTITY mail.rhysw "">
 <!ENTITY mail.gopal "">
 <!ENTITY mail.minten "">
 <!ENTITY mail.dnicol "">
 <!ENTITY _lt_ "">
 <!ENTITY _gt_ "">
 <!ENTITY _quot_ "">
 <!ENTITY _apos_ "">
 <!ENTITY _amp_ "">
 <!ENTITY nbsp "">
 <!ENTITY copy "">
 <!ENTITY root "">
<!--======================================== declared here, defined elsewhere ========================================-->

<!--======================================== don't touch this stuff ========================================-->
 <!ELEMENT ul (li)+>
 <!ELEMENT ol (li)+>
 <!ELEMENT dl (dt|dd)+>
 <!ELEMENT dt (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img)*>
 <!ELEMENT li (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img | ul | ol | dl)*>
 <!ELEMENT dd (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img | ul | ol | dl)*>
 <!ELEMENT blockquote (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img | ul | ol | dl)*><!--no nesting blockquotes-->
 <!ELEMENT pre (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a)*><!--no images in pre-->
 <!ELEMENT a (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | img)*><!--no nesting anchors-->
 <!ELEMENT content (#PCDATA | include | p | h1 | h2 | h3 | h4 | pre | blockquote)*><!--block elements only in top level-->
 <!ELEMENT p (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img)*>
 <!ELEMENT em (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img)*>
 <!ELEMENT strong (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img)*>
 <!ELEMENT code (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img)*>
 <!ELEMENT h1 (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img)*>
 <!ELEMENT h2 (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img)*>
 <!ELEMENT h3 (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img)*>
 <!ELEMENT h4 (#PCDATA | include | br | em | strong | code | a | img)*>
 <!ELEMENT br EMPTY>
 <!ELEMENT img EMPTY>
 <!ELEMENT include EMPTY>
 <!ATTLIST a title CDATA #IMPLIED name NMTOKEN #IMPLIED href CDATA #IMPLIED>
 <!ATTLIST img src CDATA #REQUIRED alt CDATA #REQUIRED align (top|middle|bottom|left|right) #IMPLIED>
 <!ATTLIST include file CDATA #REQUIRED entry NMTOKEN #IMPLIED overwrite (true|false) #IMPLIED>
<!--======================================== don't touch this stuff ========================================-->
]>

<content>
<h1>
 DotGNU - Making the Web Work for You!
</h1>
<p>
 We're building something that could be called an "operating system
 for the internet" - a collection of tools that allow software
 components to interact with each other over the internet.  The
 most impressive parts are currently <a href="&nav.pnet;">DotGNU
 Portable.NET</a> which builds a C# compiler, class library, and
 related development tools, and <a href="&nav.phpgw;">phpGroupWare</a>,
 a multi-user web-based GroupWare suite, which also serves to provide
 a good collection of webservice components, all of which can be accessed
 through XML-RPC so that you can easily integrate them into webservice
 applications of your own.
</p>
<p>
 DotGNU, a project of FreeDevelopers and GNU, is really a meta-project
 that will consist of a good number of such
 <a href="&nav.projects;">software development projects</a>. The main
 objectives of DotGNU are to build a <a href="&nav.arch;">webservices
 platform</a> and a <a href="&nav.auth;">Virtual Identities</a> system.
</p>
<!-- ===== ===== ===== NEWS ===== ===== ===== -->
<h2>
 News
</h2>
<ul>
 <li>
  July 25, 2002: The DotGNU Portable.Net 0.4.2 and Pnetlib 0.2.6
  released . Here is the mailing list
  <a href="&nav.mail.pipermail;developers/2002-July/003795.html">announcement</a>.
 </li>
 <li>
  June 29, 2002: The DotGNU Project announces the second 36 hour
  meet-a-thon on June 29th - June 30th from 1000 UTC Saturday to 2200
  UTC Sunday. Here is the
  <a href="&nav.mail.pipermail;developers/2002-June/003511.html">announcement</a>.
 </li>
 <li>
  May 27, 2002: The DotGNU Project officially endorses the use of
  the Jabber Protocols.  Here is the
  <a href="&nav.mail.pipermail;announce/2002-May/000004.html">announcement</a>.
 </li>
 <li>
  March 23, 2002: Rhys Weatherley, the maintainer of pnet and
  pnetlib, has appointed the following two people to special roles:
  <ul>
   <li>
    Gopal V. - Pnetlib Lead Developer At Large (LDAL)
   </li>
   <li>
    Peter Minten - Lead Developer for System.Net
   </li>
  </ul>
  The role of a lead developer is to co-ordinate work and
  patches in their area.  Rhys will continue to act in the role of
  LDAL for pnet and treecc.  We also have several active CVS
  committers and patch submitters, who have been working tirelessly
  in their respective areas.  Some of these may also be appointed as
  lead developers as the need arises.
 </li>
 <li>
  January 2, 2002:
  <a href="&nav.mail.pipermail;developers/2002-January/001599.html">
  This Year in DotGNU - No 1 (2001: The Year When DotGNU Was Born)</a>
 </li>
</ul>
<!-- ===== ===== ===== NEWS ===== ===== ===== -->
<h1>
 DotGNU - Keeping You from Getting Tangled in a Net!
</h1>
<p>
 The DotGNU project was originally started in reaction to Microsoft's
 .NET strategy, for which it will be a complete replacement (and not
 just a Free Software implementation). The parts of .NET strategy about
 which we are most concerned are Microsoft's attempts to gain control of
 the internet and its users. Parts of this strategy, including the plan
 to unleash a <include file="navlinks.xml" entry="hailstorm" /> have
 been dropped, <include file="navlinks.xml" entry="hailstorm.whynot" />
 On other fronts, Microsoft is still working hard to entangle everyone
 in their .NET -- In contrast, the goal of DotGNU is to give computer
 users full freedom to use the internet as they want.  For example, the
 DotGNU approach to <a href="&nav.web_services;">"web services"</a> will
 make it possible for end users to run webservice software on their own
 PC, so that the users are not forced to migrate their data to the
 webservice servers.
</p>
<p>
 DotGNU will use a decentralized paradigm:  No single company, server or
 entity will control authorization.  This avoids privacy problems like
 those recently pointed out in
 <include file="navlinks.xml" entry="letter.epic.on.passport" />
</p>
<p>
 Furthermore, DotGNU will emphasize security, it will use encryption
 wherever possible to keep user data secure and hidden. (According to
 the article
 <include file="navlinks.xml" entry="risks.of.passport" />[1],
 Microsoft's approach has some fundamental problems in the area of
 security.  In fact it appears that
 <include file="navlinks.xml" entry="passport.data.is.cleartext" />,
 a huge security risk.)  Because of entirely unrelated, serious
 security problems,
 <include file="navlinks.xml" entry="ms.forced.disable.wallet" /> as
 Marc Slemko
 <include file="navlinks.xml" entry="published.wallet.exploit" />
</p>
<p>
 There are no real remaining traditional competitors to MS, and the US
 government recently failed to contain MS, so the field is left to us. MS has
 announced that it has "bet the company" on .Net, because "Webservices"
 represents the future, and Windows and MS Office will become progressively
 less important. So DotGNU stands between where MS is and where it wants to
 be. Therefore DotGNU and .Net represents the ultimate showdown between
 proprietary and Free Software.
</p>
<h2>
 Don't read unpublished Microsoft information
</h2>
<p>
 In order to avoid falling into any legal traps, please be extremely
 careful to avoid reading any unpublished information from Microsoft.
</p>
<p>
 We ask every contributor to disclose exactly how much exposure they've
 had to Microsoft stuff, and make them commit to report any additional
 exposure immediately.  Whenever there is even the slightest shade of a
 possible problem,  the contributor needs to refrain from contributing
 until our legal team has been established and it has provided
 appropriate advice.
</p>
<h2>
 Weekly IRC Meetings
</h2>
<p>
 DotGNU holds weekly meetings to discuss any issues
 of relevance; to allow the developers to catch up
 with each other; and to allow new members to ask
 questions and find out how to join in.
</p>
<p>
 The meetings are conducted via IRC in the channel
 times:
</p>
<pre>
    Saturday 1000 UTC
    Saturday 2200 UTC
</pre>
<p>
 The first is best for DotGNU members east of UTC
 and the second is best for DotGNU members west
 of UTC.  Some of the key DotGNU members attend
 both meetings.
</p>
<p>
 The logs of #dotgnu are always available here:
 <include file="navlinks.xml" entry="irc.dotgnu.logs" />
</p>
<p>
 Note: the times are UTC, not GMT.  That is, they
 do not include daylight savings adjustments during
 the northern summer.  If you use the GNU operating system
 (e.g. GNU/Linux, the popular combination of the GNU system
 with the kernel called Linux) or a Unix system,
 then the command "date; date -u" will give you
 your current time in both local and UTC, allowing
 you do determine when the next meeting will occur.
</p>
<h2>
 DotGNU technical specifications
</h2>
<p>
 We have started working on technical specifications for the DotGNU
 system.  So far the following documents are available:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>
  <a href="&root;spec/rls.htm">Resource Locator Strings</a>
 </li>
 <li>
  <a href="&root;spec/tokens.htm">Tokens</a>
 </li>
</ul>
<h2>
 Subscribe to the mailing lists
</h2>
<p>
 For a quick introduction to some key points that have been discussed,
 please refer to the messages referred in this
 <a href="&nav.mail.pipermail;developers/2001-August/000719.html">summary
 post by Antonio Ognio</a>. (Such summary posts are definitely
 worthwhile, and the maintainer of this page is very open to
 adding links to more such summaries.)
</p>
<p>
 The DotGNU project has the following mailing lists:
</p>
<ul>
 <li>
  The <a href="&nav.mail.developers;">DEVELOPERS</a>
  mailing list for general development discussions. For example, feature
  requests are discussed here.
 </li>
 <li>
  The <a href="&nav.mail.announce;">ANNOUNCE</a>
  mailing list for press releases and other important announcements
  concerning the DotGNU system.
 </li>
 <li>
  The <a href="&nav.mail.auth;">AUTH</a>
  mailing list for moving forward with quickly creating a first,
  useful incarnation of the <a href="&nav.auth;">DotGNU Virtual
  Identities</a> system.
 </li>
 <li>
  The <a href="&nav.mail.arch;">ARCH</a>
  for moving forward with designing the architecture of the DotGNU
  system and <a href="&nav.arch;">DotGNU platform</a>.  This list is
  working on long-term stuff.
 </li>
 <li>
  The <a href="&nav.mail.biz;">BIZPLAN</a>
  mailing list for everyone who is interested in DotGNU BizPlan.
 </li>
 <li>
  The <a href="&nav.mail.website;">WEBSITE</a>
  mailing list which supports the webmaster of the DotGNU website.
 </li>
</ul>
<p>
 Please avoid cross-posting to multiple of these lists.  If something
 needs a broader audience than just one of the specialized mailing
 lists, post it to DEVELOPERS.
</p>
<h2>
 General Information about the DotGNU Project
</h2>
<p>
 DotGNU is being developed jointly under the auspices
 of <a href="&misc.freedev;">FreeDevelopers</a>
 and the <a href="&misc.gnu;">GNU project</a>.
 The DotGNU system will be a well-integrated part of the
 <a href="&misc.gnu;">GNU system</a> and it will
 also be made available to the users of all other
 widely-used operation systems.  If you wish to receive
 important announcements about the DotGNU project, please
 subscribe to the <a href="&nav.mail.announce;">DotGNU
 announcements mailing list</a>.
</p>
<h3>
 Where will DotGNU compete with the Microsoft .Net
 and Hailstorm products?
</h3>
<p>
 In all areas.
</p>
<p>
 Just like it's the goal of the <a href="&misc.gnu;">GNU project</a>
 to create a complete operating system that makes it completely
 unnecessary to use a non-free operating system like e.g. Microsoft
 Windows, it's the goal of the DotGNU project to be a complete
 competitor to Microsoft's ".Net initiative" and "Hailstorm" products.
</p>
<p>
 The DotGNU project will compete with Microsoft for end-users,
 business customers and developers.
</p>
<p>
 Microsoft Windows had a huge head start over GNU/Linux in terms
 of user-friendliness to end users.  In spite of Microsoft's vast
 resources, GNU/Linux is already better than Microsoft Windows in
 some areas, and catching up fast in most others.
</p>
<p>
 We believe that the same kind of success story is possible with
 the DotGNU project.  The main difference is that this time,
 Microsoft doesn't have such a big head start.
</p>
<h3>
 What will DotGNU do that those products also want to do?
</h3>
<p>
 The DotGNU system will deliver the same and better benefits to end
 users and business customers, but we will be very careful that no
 company or other organization can gain any monopoly-like power over
 the system.
</p>
<h3>
 How will DotGNU be different from those Microsoft products?
</h3>
<p>
 The DotGNU project will use good ideas from Microsoft as a
 source of inspiration, and Microsoft will probably also use
 good ideas from the DotGNU project as a source of inspiration.
</p>
<p>
 The big difference is that there is a single company (Microsoft)
 in the center of the universe of the ".Net initiative" and
 "Hailstorm" products,  while the DotGNU project creates a
 framework where anyone who wants can offer every service.
 For example, with DotGNU every Internet Service Provider (ISP)
 can offer the equivalent of Microsoft's "Passport" service,
 and the ISP can customize and modify this service according to
 their customers' needs.
</p>
<p>
 In the DotGNU system, the paradigm of decentralization goes so far
 that whenever an Application Service Provider (ASP) makes a program
 available to a customer, the customer is not forced to use the program
 only on the Application Service Provider's computers.  The customers
 can download the program and use it locally on their own PCs.  This is
 in strong contrast to the Microsoft's vision for
 <a href="&nav.web_services;">"web services"</a>.
</p>
<h3>
 What do you guys think about Hailstorm and Passport?
</h3>
<p>
 Hailstorms tend to be destructive.  And one should not need to use a
 passport in one's own country.<sup>2</sup>
</p>
<h3>
 What do you guys think of Microsoft's .Net and Hailstorm efforts?
</h3>
<p>
 Dangerous stuff.  It is often said that the price of freedom is
 eternal vigilance.<sup>3</sup> Unless we counter them, Microsoft's efforts
 are not only a threat to Free Software, they are also extremely
 dangerous tools in the hands of any Evil Government that wants
 to make their citizens unfree.
</p>
<p>
 &nbsp;
</p>
<h4>
 References:
</h4>
<ol>
 <li>
  David P. Kormann and Aviel D. Rubin,
  <include file="navlinks.xml" entry="risks.of.passport" />,
  Elsevier Science Press, volume 33, pages 51-58, 2000.
 </li>
 <li>
  The quote "Hailstorms tend to be destructive.  And one should not
  need to use a passport in one's own country." is taken from a
  <a href="&nav.mail.pipermail;arch/2001-July/000025.html">post
  by David Sugar on the arch mailing list</a>.
 </li>
 <li>
  This truth was popularized by Thomas Jefferson (1743 - 1826).
  The original source seems to be a speech by John Philpot Curran,
  who said "It is the common fate of the indolent to see their
  rights become a prey to the active. The condition upon which God hath
  given liberty to man is eternal vigilance; which condition if he
  break, servitude is at once the consequence of his crime and the
  punishment of his guilt." - <em>John Philpot Curran: Speech upon the
  Right of Election, 1790. (Speeches. Dublin, 1808.)</em>
 </li>
</ol>
</content>
