<content>
<a name="28-02-2004">
	<h2>March 6 6-3-2004: C Compiler: Significant Progress and Call For Volunteers</h2>
</a>
<p>
The new C compiler type system has been checked in.  Type layout is
now totally dynamic; the IL binary will automatically adapt itself
to the runtime engine it is running on.  This means that DotGNU is
bringing true "write once, run anywhere" functionality to C,
running on top of standard CLR implementations.  Unlike Microsoft's
C compiler, whose output will only run on i386-based Windows
systems, ours will run portable ANSI C code on any platform that
has a CLR, be it 32-bit or 64-bit, little-endian or big.
 </p>
<p>
Simple examples of C programs can be compiled to IL now, and
volunteers are needed to work on the standard C library so that
more programs and libraries can be compiled.  Our eventual goal is
to bring a large body of Free Software libraries and programs to
the CLI environment, vastly increasing the range of functionality
beyond the small number of libraries currently defined for C#.
</p>
<a name="28-02-2004">
	<h2>February 28-2-2004: .NET Developer's Journal Readers' Choice Awards 2003</h2>
</a>
<p>
We were mentioned in the ".NET Developer's Journal Readers' Choice Awards 
2003", achieving third runner up in the "Best .NET Build Tools/Installers" 
category and second runner up in the "Best .NET CLI" category.  The full 
details are at the following URL:<br/>
<a href="http://www.sys-con.com/2002/PR/02252004.cfm">http://www.sys-con.com/2002/PR/02252004.cfm</a>
</p>

<a name="27-02-2004">
	<h2>February 27-2-2004: Interview with nb on gnu-friends.org</h2>
</a>
<p>
Gnu-friends has an interview about the history of DotGNU and nb's views on
Free Software philosophy:
<a href="http://gnu-friends.org/story/2004/2/27/15415/3365">http://gnu-friends.org/story/2004/2/27/15415/3365</a>
</p>

<a name="11-02-2004">
	<h2>February 11-2-2004: "Darwinports" packages of Portable.Net 0.6.2
            for Mac OS X</h2>
</a>
<p>
Thanks to the efforts of olegb, "DarwinPorts" packages of DotGNU
Portable.NET 0.6.2, including System.Windows.Forms, are now available.
To install, use "port install pnet; port install pnetlib; port install ml-pnet"
</p>
<a name="3-01-2004">
	<h2>January 3-1-2004: Portable.Net 0.6.2 released</h2>
</a>
<p>
Version 0.6.2 of DotGNU Portable.NET has been released with many
enhancements particularly in the area of <code>System.Windows.Forms</code>,
with improvements to most controls, fonts, MDI, tree views, and file dialogs.
Please use the
<a href="http://www.southern-storm.com.au/portable_net.html">Southern Storm
site</a> for now for downloading it, as we are currently unable to update
<code>ftp.gnu.org</code>
</p>

<a name="11-01-2004">
	<h2>January 11-1-2004: Portable.Net on Playstation 2</h2>
</a>
<p>
Thanks to the efforts of Adam Ballai and Lance Gilbert
DotGNU Portable.Net is now running on Sony Playstation 2
(which has a little endian "R5900 V3.1" MIPS cpu.)
</p>

<a name="12-01-2004">
	<h2>January 12-1-2004: DotGNU at LCA2004</h2>
</a>
<p>
Four DotGNU'ers have made it to LCA2004 in Adelaide, Australia.
A group photo is <a
href="http://www.southern-storm.com.au/download/dotgnu-quorum.jpg">here</a>.
From the left, we have Andrew Mitchell (ajmitch), Rhys Weatherley (rhysw), 
Chris Smith (cds), and Dave Hall (skwashd, who wishes to remain anonymous for 
reasons unknown).
</p>

<a name="13-01-2004">
	<h2>January 13-1-2004: website update</h2>
</a>
<p>
All official GNU websites (which are on www.gnu.org or tightly synchronized
with www.gnu.org, where in the example of DotGNU, our website is at
<a
href="http://www.gnu.org/projects/dotgnu/">http://www.gnu.org/projects/dotgnu/</a>)
were in hiatus between mid-November 2003 and January 2004 due to a
security breach at an important server of the Free Software Foundation,
and the resulting need to set up a much more secure system.  The new
system is available now, although it seems to have a bug which
prevents the <code>www.gnu.org</code> version of the DotGNU website from being
updated.  Since the DotGNU project has important news to share, and I don't
have much hope of this project-specific bug being treated with priority (it may
have to do with DotGNU being under <code>/projects</code> on
<code>www.gnu.org</code> and not under <code>/software</code> like almost
everything else), I'm now updating <code>dotgnu.org</code> without waiting for
the savannah webcvs bug to be fixed.
</p>

<a name="06-11-2003">
	<h2>November 6-11-2003: DotGNU Snake!</h2>
</a>
<p>
Support for the upcoming "Whidbey" System.Console routines has been added to 
Portable.NET, and there is a simple "Snake" game that demonstrates how to 
use it.  A screenshot is <a href="screenshot13.html">here</a>
</p>


<a name="04-11-2003">
	<h2>November 4-11-2003: DotGNU 0.1 Release Announcement</h2>
</a>
<p>
	The <a href="release.html">release announcement</a> for the
	DotGNU 0.1 CD-ROM release has been posted.
</p>
<a name="02-11-2003">
	<h2>November 2-11-2003: Embedding X applications in Xsharp</h2>
</a>
<p>
It is now possible to embed any X application as a child widget within an 
Xsharp application.  The pnetlib CVS tree includes "XClockEmbed.cs" as an 
example of doing this for "xclock", and <a href="screenshot12.html">this
screenshot</a> shows both "gedit" (a GNOME app) and "kcalc" (a KDE app) running
as two children of the same Xsharp main window.  This is important because the
next version of WinForms will have a HTML web browser control widget, and
we will want to embed an existing third-part Free Software web browser, and
not write a web browser from scratch in C#.
</p>
<a name="01-11-2003">
	<h2>November 1-11-2003: DotGNU 0.1 BitTorrent downloads</h2>
</a>
<p>
BitTorrents for DotGNU 0.1 are available now at
<a
href="http://download.freedom.biz/dotgnu/">http://download.freedom.biz/dotgnu/</a>.
You can download the gzip'ed DotGNU 0.1 CD-ROM iso image (219 MB) or
the following binary packages: Debian GNU/Linux .deb packages,
RedHat/Fedora (S)RPMS, Mandrake9 rpm packages, FreeBSD packages,
Mac OS X packages, and also Installer packages for the MS Windows system.
</p>
<a name="30-10-2003">
	<h2>October 30-10-2003: ftp.gnu.org update</h2>
</a>
<p>
	Up-to-date source tarballs for Portable.NET are again available from
        <a href="ftp://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/dotgnu/pnet/">ftp.gnu.org</a> and
	its mirrors.
</p>
<a name="28-10-2003">
	<h2>October 28-10-2003: DGEE 0.1.6 is released</h2>
</a>
<p>
	<a
	href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2003-October/011731.html">DGEE
	0.1.6 has been released</a>.  The DotGNU 0.1 release will follow
	very soon.
</p>
<a name="15-10-2003">
	<h2>October 15-10-2003: DotGNU Portable.NET 0.6.0 released</h2>
</a>
<p>
	Version 0.6.0 of
	<a href="http://www.southern-storm.com.au/portable_net.html">DotGNU
	Portable.NET</a> has been released.  This is the release which will
	go onto the DotGNU 0.1 CD.  It contains lots of bug fixes,
	functionality was missing in earlier versions, and huge improvements
        in System.Windows.Forms.  The full release announcement is
	<a href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2003-October/011609.html">here</a>.
</p>
<a name="10-10-2003">
	<h2>October 10-10-2003: Feature freeze</h2>
</a>
<p>
	A feature freeze for Portable.NET is now in effect, leading up to
	the DotGNU 0.1 release, which will be "really soon now".
	During feature freeze, bugs in existing code will be fixed if they are
	either easy to do, or there is no way for a programmer to work around
	them.  Anything that may impact stability will be deferred until after
	DotGNU 0.1.
</p>
<a name="09-10-2003">
	<h2>October 09-10-2003: pnet's SWF runs also on MS Windows</h2>
</a>
<p>
	Portable.net now runs pnetlib's System.Windows.Forms also
	on the Microsoft Windows System.  This is a major achievement
	in the area of portability.  There is a
	<a href="screenshot10.html">screenshot</a>.
</p>
<a name="06-09-2003">
	<h2>September 06-09-2003: Portable.NET 0.5.12 released</h2>
</a>
<p>
	Portable.NET 0.5.12 has been released, and is
	<a href="http://www.southern-storm.com.au/portable_net.html">available
	for download</a>.  This is mostly a bug fix release, heading up towards
	0.6.0, but with substantial improvements throughout the system. 
	Particularly Winforms (many thanks to Neil Cawse).  Please check out
	the new, improved
	<a href="http://dotgnu.org/pnetlib-status/">pnetlib-status pages</a>,
	and help us nail the rest of the core classes prior to 0.6.0.
</p>
<a name="26-08-2003">
	<h2>August 26-08-2003: 1st International DotGNU Collaborative Coding Competition</h2>
</a>
<p>
	The DotGNU project is holding an international competition
	in the area of collaboratively implementing
	<a href="http://wiki.dotgnu.org/SystemWindowsForms">System.Windows.Forms</a>.
	Besides the chance of winning one of fifteen monetary prizes
	totalling US$ 4500, participants get the good feeling of having
	contributed to setting the IT world free from the dominion of a
	certain monopolistic company.  The full announcement is
	<a href="competition.html">here</a>.
</p>
<a name="09-08-2003">
	<h2>August 09-08-2003: DotGNU 0.1 to be released end-September</h2>
</a>
<p>
	At today's irc meeting, the release date for DotGNU 0.1
	has been fixed at end-September.  For Portable.NET the
	goals are to get pnetC to basic usefulness, fix as many
	system.xml bugs as we can, and make the core button/textbox/scroll
	widgets work in winforms.
</p>
<a name="26-07-2003">
	<h2>July 26-07-2003: Portable.NET 0.5.10 released</h2>
</a>
<p>
	Breaking the tradition, which required a 0.6.0 this time , the 
	pnet developers have decided to put out 0.5.10, 0.5.12, etc, 
	as release candidates for 0.6.0, which will be part of DotGNU 0.1.
</p>
<p>
	A lot has happened this release.  The System.Windows.Forms namespace is
	coming along well. The DotGNU community has chipped in more than its
	fair share of it this release - particularly Simon Guindon, Neil Cawse, 
	Richard Baumann, Ian Fung, Cecilio Pardo, and the relentless Gopal V.
	Threading now works very well (thanks to Thong Nguyen aka tum) and 
	Reflection.Emit (Richard Baumann) too. The C compiler has advanced 
	enough to compile most C programs. The pnetC now has significant bits
	of glibc and is looking for people to help port the rest of glibc here.
	The CVM unroller was also rewritten into a generic framework that should
	be much easier to port to new architectures.
</p>
<p>
	Read the full NEWS entries 
<a href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2003-July/011079.html">here</a>.
		here and download it from <a href="http://dotgnu.org/downloads.html">here.</a>
</p>

<a name="24-07-2003">
	<h2>July 24-07-2003: Portable.net runs Component Pascal </h2>
</a>
<p>
	Gardens Point Component Pascal (GPCP) works with Portable.net. 
	GPCP is interesting because the compiler and runtime are completely 
	hosted inside the CLI environment, using ilasm to generate the 
	output binaries. Read more about GPCP 
	<a href="http://www.citi.qut.edu.au/research/plas/projects/cp_files/ComponentPascal.html">here</a> 
	and the instructions for using it with 
	Portable.net 
<a href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2003-July/011047.html">here</a>.
	
</p>
<a name="18-07-2003">
	<h2>July 18-07-2003: TreeCC 0.2.6 released</h2>
</a>
<p>
	TreeCC 0.2.6 was released with minor modifications , which
	adds an additional GC allocated node model to the original HEAP 
	allocated (malloc) model and namespace support to C++ output.
	Other minor bug fixes and improvements go along. Read the full
	announcement 
<a href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2003-July/011014.html">here</a>.
</p>
<a name="14-07-2003">
	<h2>July 14-07-2003: PPC Speed Gains in DotGNU Portable.NET</h2>
</a>
<p>
	Portable.NET on the PPC has recently doubled in speed due to the
	use of manual register assignments on that platform. The speed gains
	will be noticeable once the PPC unroller port has been completed.
	For more details, read the mailing list 
<a href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/pnet-developers/2003-July/000405.html">thread</a>.
</p>
<a name="12-07-2003">
	<h2>July 12-07-2003: Generic Unroller in DotGNU Portable.NET</h2>
</a>
<p>
	The generic unroller has finally hit pnet cvs. The unroller is
	responsible for producing native code (much like a JIT) for the pnet
	runtime. The generic unroller separates the CPU specific details of
	native code generation, like opcode values and register ordering, from
	generic features, like register allocation, greatly simplifying the
	process of porting the unroller to new platforms. The ARM and x86
	ports are already working and support for IA-64, PPC, and Alpha is in
	the works. For more details, read the mailing list 
<a href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/pnet-developers/2003-July/000399.html">thread</a>.
</p>
<a name="05-07-2003">
	<h2>July 05-07-2003: DotGNU Manifesto</h2>
</a>
<p>
The <a href="manifesto.html">DotGNU Manifesto</a> is now official,
and consequently the version number has been changed to 1.0.  (There
are no other changes from draft version 0.4).
</p>
<a name="29-06-2003">
	<h2>June 29-06-2003: Threading in DotGNU Portable.NET</h2>
</a>
<p>
Thanks to the works of Thong Nguyen (tum), threading is working in
DotGNU Portable.NET now.  For more details please refer to the
<a href="http://wiki.dotgnu.org/PortableNet/Threads">PortableNet/Threads
wiki page</a>.
</p>
<a name="27-06-2003">
	<h2>June 27-06-2003: Video Clip of System.Windows.Forms on handhelds</h2>
</a>
<p>
We now have a
<a href="http://demo.dotgnu.org/~minddog/hellotest.avi">video clip</a>
showing one of the famous DotGNU coding fingers
testing System.Windows.Forms on an Ipaq handheld computer with
DotGNU Portable.NET
</p>
<a name="17-06-2003">
	<h2>June 17-06-2003: Portable.NET 0.5.8 released</h2>
</a>
<p>
A lot of things have happened since the last Portable.NET release.  The Java
and Visual Basic language front-ends for cscc have been added to the system,
and a huge number of new classes have been implemented in pnetlib, including
support for IPv6 and IrDA networking.
</p>
<p>
We have also begun implementation of the System.Windows.Forms library,
built on top of the X11 library.  This means that it will be able to run
on any X11-capable system.  Currently tested to work on x86-based GNU/Linux
systems and ppc-based MacOS X systems.
</p>
<p>
We are looking for volunteers to help us implement the "x11-winforms"
library as quickly as possible, and to test it on as many platforms as
possible.
</p>
<p>
Finally, the ml-pnet project has been started to provide ports of certain
Mono C# libraries.  System.Data (ADO.NET) currently works, and we hope to
have System.Web (ASP.NET) working soon.
</p>
<p>
The full announcement is <a
href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2003-June/010763.html">here</a>.
</p>
<a name="13-06-2003">
	<h2>June 16-06-2003: X11-WinForms support for OS X</h2>
</a>
<p>
	Portable.net System.Windows.Forms is now working on OS X as well
        as GNU/Linux.  Screenshots of test programs on OS X are
	<a href="screenshot4.html">here</a>,
	<a href="screenshot5.html">here</a> and
	<a href="screenshot6.html">here</a>.  We ask OS X developers to help
	us with continuing this work.
</p>
<a name="13-06-2003">
	<h2>June 13-06-2003: WinForms support for Portable.net </h2>
</a>
<p>
	Portable.net has started work on the System.Windows.Forms namespace
	and a simple forms example has been run on the platform. The WinForms
	effort is to proceed as a new lightweight toolkit based on System.Drawing
	rather than as a UI wrapper system. This will allow it to be compatible
	to the specifications even when the native UI is different. Currently 
	a system based on X11 drawing apis is being developed. Read all 
	about it <a href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2003-June/010715.html">here</a> 
	or see a <a href="screenshot3.html">screenshot</a>.
</p>
<a name="06-06-2003">
	<h2>June 6-06-2003: Postgresql provider for ML-Pnet</h2>
</a>
<p>
	The DotGNU Portable.net project now has added a full capability
	Managed Postgresql Provider thanks to the efforts of the 
	<a href="http://gborg.postgresql.org/project/npgsql/">Npgsql</a>
	project admin Francisco Figueiredo Jr. The detailed instructions
	are available from the <a href="http://gborg.postgresql.org/project/npgsql/news/newsfull.php?news_id=117"> Npgsql News Page </a>.
</p>
<a name="02-06-2003">
	<h2>June 2-06-2003: Three Quarters of a Million Lines!</h2>
</a>
<p>
The DotGNU Portable.NET project has passed the "750,000 lines of code"
milestone. Read the full anouncement
<a href="http://www.dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2003-June/010653.html">here</a>.
</p>
<a name="29-05-2003">
	<h2>May 29-05-2003: Support for IPv6 and IrDa protocols</h2>
</a>
<p>
	Portable.NET now has support for IPv6 (the "next generation" internet
	protocol which fixes a number of problems with the current version,
	in particular the limited number of available IPv4 addresses) and
	the IrDa sockets protocol (so that now you can use DotGNU to build
	networks between infrared capable handhelds and workstations).  With
	Portable.NET, IrDA is supported in all versions where the OS kernel
	supports it, not just handhelds.  (This differs from Microsoft's
	version of .NET where IrDa capability is not available in the
	workstation-level SDK.)
</p>
<a name="24-05-2003">
	<h2>May 25-05-2003: Pnetlib status pages now against .NET 1.1 </h2>
</a>
<p>
	The <a href="http://dotgnu.org/pnetlib-status/">pnetlib-status</a> 
	pages have been updated to include comparisons to the .NET 1.1 standard.
	Only 474 classes to go, so please pick a class , any class and lend
	a hand. We're nearly there !.
</p>
<a name="17-05-2003a">
	<h2>May 17-05-2003: It's raining compilers this weekend</h2>
</a>
<p>
Version 0.0.2 of the
DotGNU JAVA compiler has been released and integrated into pnet cvs.
</p>
<a name="17-05-2003b">
	<h2>May 17-05-2003: Compiler for minimalistic programming language and demo webservice</h2>
</a>
<p>
Following a complaint that DotGNU did not yet have a compiler for a
<a href="http://www.muppetlabs.com/~breadbox/bf/">minimalistic programming
language</a>, such a compiler was quickly created, together with a demo
webservice.  The code is in pnet cvs and can serve as a simple example of
a cscc plugin.
</p>
<a name="16-05-2003">
	<h2>May 16-05-2003: Hello World in Visual Basic.NET</h2>
</a>
<p>
The beginnings of Visual Basic.NET support are now in pnet cvs.  Try
"cscc -o hello hello.vb" and run with "ilrun hello".
If you would like to help out on the VB project, then there is lots of work 
still to do:
</p>
<ol>
<li>Building the treecc nodes in the parser for the remaining syntax.</li>
<li>VB-specific semantic analysis and codegen routines.</li>
<li>Flesh out the standard library in pnetlib/Basic.</li>
<li>Build test cases for the compiler in cscctest.</li>
<li>Build test cases for the standard library in pnetlib/Basic.</li>
</ol>
<p>
1 and 2 require cscc compiler skills - if you're interested in learning the 
compiler, then this is the time to start.  The Java, VB, C#, and C front ends 
will all need lots of eager beavers over the next few months.
3, 4, and 5 are easier, mainly requiring C# and/or VB programming skills.  
Grep for "TODO" under pnetlib/Basic, check out the documentation for the 
Microsoft.VisualBasic namespace on msdn.microsoft.com, and send in those 
patches!
</p>
<a name="05-05-2003">
	<h2>May 05-05-2003: Code unroller for ARM CPUs available</h2>
</a>
<p>
Rhys has written a CVM code unroller for ARM/StrongARM platforms.
An unroller uses some simple JIT techniques to translate commonly-used CVM
instructions into native code.  The result is about a 2-3 times improvement
in performance on ARM, compared with the default direct threaded
configuration.
For more details, read the
<a href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2003-May/010505.html">announcement</a>.
</p>
<a name="03-05-2003">
	<h2>May 03-05-2003: Portable.NET 0.5.6 released</h2>
</a>
<p>
Besides "mscorlib.dll" being now 100% signature compatible with the
corresponding assembly in version 1.1 (see previous news item), the
other big news is that the library can now be built in multiple configurations
with "./configure --with-profile=X", where "X" is one of the following:
</p>
<blockquote>
full, ecma, compact, compact-fp, kernel, kernel-fp, tiny, tiny-fp
</blockquote>
<p>
For detailed NEWS entries and signed md5sum's, read the
<a href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2003-May/010501.html">announcement</a>.
</p>
<a name="26-04-2003b">
	<h2>Apr 26-04-2003: 100% signature compatibility of mscorlib.dll</h2>
</a>
<p>
The lowest-level library within pnetlib, "mscorlib.dll", is 
now signature compatible with the corresponding assembly in version 1.1 of 
the .NET Framework SDK.  Every class, every method, every interop marker 
attribute, and every silly little enumerated constant.  All of it!
Read the <A href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2003-April/010460.html">announcement</A>
and please help with testing!
</p>
<a name="10-04-2003">
	<h2>Apr 10-04-2003: New DotGNU manifesto draft</h2>
</a>
<p>
 RMS has responded to the
 <a href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2003-April/010392.html">new
 DotGNU Manifesto draft</a> with the words "It looks good to me".
</p>
<a name="07-04-2003">
	<h2>Apr 07-04-2003: Installer for MS Windows System available for download</h2>
</a>
<p>
	Bob Johnson has compiled <code>DotGNU Portable.NET</code> and
	<code>TREECC</code> for the
	Microsoft Windows system and created nice "installer" packages.
	Thanks, Bob!
</p>
<a name="04-04-2003">
	<h2>Apr 04-04-2003: Discussion of W3C Patents Policy</h2>
</a>
<p>
	A thoughtful discussion of W3C's new proposed Patents Policy,
	and why it is unacceptable from DotGNU's perspective, is 
	<a href="http://www.kuro5hin.org/story/2003/4/2/8593/27458">unfolding
	at kuro5hin.org</a> following an opinion piece posted by
	<a href="http://wiki.dotgnu.org/DotGNUPeople/NorbertBollow">nb</a>
	aka <em>bizcoach</em>.
</p>
<a name="31-03-2003">
	<h2>Mar 31-03-2003: DGEE Release 0.1.4</h2>
</a>
<p>
	Version 0.1.4 of <a href="dgee.html">DGEE</a>, the DotGNU Execution
	Environment has been released.  There is now full XML-RPC support,
	multiple VM support, multiple webservice language support,
	auto-generation of client XML-RPC code from assembly, and better memory
	management.  An installation helper "dgeediagnose" is available for
	sorting out ipc resource issues.
</p>
<a name="31-03-2003">
	<h2>Mar 31-03-2003: Portable.Net Release 0.5.4</h2>
</a>
<p>
	DotGNU Portable.Net 0.5.4 has been released.  Pnetlib 0.5.4
	and TreeCC 0.2.4 have been released along with it.  The high points are
	the beginnings of support for Generic IL and Reflection.Emit, with lots
	of little bug fixes here and there.  Read more
	<a href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2003-March/010286.html">
		here
	</a> or go get it from <a href="downloads.html">here</a>.
</p>
<a name="28-03-2003">
	<h2>Mar 28-03-2003: Portable.Net Release Timetable </h2>
</a>
<p>
	The Portable.NET project, which is central for DotGNU's efforts
	for compatibility with Microsoft's .NET, now has a firm
	<a href="http://www.dotgnu.org/pipermail/pnet-developers/2003-March/000083.html">
	release schedule</a>.  Full support for ECMA standards 334
	and 335 is expected by the end of June 2003.
</p>
<a name="01-03-2003">
	<h2>Mar 01-03-2003: DotGNU Wiki Pages </h2>
</a>
<p>
	DotGNU now has a collaborative webpage at 
	<a href="http://wiki.dotgnu.org">wiki.dotgnu.org</a> and 
	is building a collection of information related to dotgnu and
	its subprojects. Adam Ballai has been central to this
	development and has set this up . So everyone is invited to
	chip in and go wiki.
</p>
<a name="22-02-2003">
	<h2>Feb 22-02-2003: Generic IL support </h2>
</a>
<p>
	The DotGNU Portable.net base tools now have support for Generic IL.
	Portable.NET is the first Free Software implementation of the CLI
	to release real support for Generic IL. It includes the assembler
	and disassembler for now. The compiler is being worked upon to
	support generic C# in the near future. Read all about what's done
	and what's not in 
	<a href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2003-February/009918.html">
	this mail
	</a>.
</p> 
<a name="08-02-2003">
	<h2>Feb 08-02-2003: Portable.Net Release 0.5.2 </h2>
</a>
<p>
	DotGNU Portable.Net 0.5.2 has been released. Pnetlib 0.5.2
	and TreeCC 0.2.2 have been released along with it. This release
	has been a quantum jump in portability with platforms as varied
	as x86,IA-64,S390,arm,PA-RISC etc being supported. Read about the 
	rest of the new whistles and bells 
	<a href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2003-February/009761.html">
		here
	</a> or go get it from <a href="downloads.html">here</a>.
</p>
<a name="27-01-2003">
	<h2>Jan 27-01-2003: The RSS Feed is on !</h2>
</a>
<p>
	The Dotgnu website team have decided that RSS is the 
	way to go and true to our webservice initiatives we now
	have a cool RSS feed. <a href="http://dotgnu.org/index.rdf">
	Syndicate !</a>
</p>
<a name="18-01-2003">
	<h2>Jan 18-01-2003: The Portable.net papers</h2>
</a>
<p>
	A paper about ``The Design of the Portable.NET Interpreter'' is
	being presented by Rhys Weatherly at the Linux Conference 2003, 
	Australia. The paper will discuss the various levels of optimizations
	that are selected platform-wise to make the Portable.net interpreter
	faster and yet still remain truly portable. Read the entire paper 
	in PDF 
	<a href="http://www.southern-storm.com.au/download/pnet-engine.pdf">
	here. </a> 
</p>
<a name="16-01-2003">
	<h2>Jan 16-01-2003: QMahjong Qt# Demo </h2>
</a>
<p>
	Rhys Weatherly has brought out a good demo of Portable.net with a 
	Mahjong game with Qt#. It works with the 
	<a href="http://www.southern-storm.com.au/portable_net.html">
		Portable.net 0.5.0
		</a>
		release and the 
	<a href="http://qtcsharp.sourceforge.net/">Qt# 0.6</a>. Get the sources
	from
	<a href="http://www.southern-storm.com.au/download/mahjongg-0.0.1.tar.gz">
		mahjong-0.0.1.tar.gz
	</a> or see a screenshot at 
	<a href="http://qtcsharp.sourceforge.net/screen/mahjongg-0.6.png">
		Qt# website
	</a>. Play on ! 
</p>
<a name="11-01-2003">
	<h2>Jan 11-01-2003: DotGNU Releases</h2>
</a>
<p>
	The DotGNU Portable.net and DotGNU DGEE are coming up with
	releases today. The Portable.net is having a milestone release
	of 0.5.0 . Read all about the Portable.net release
	<a href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2003-January/009464.html">
		here
	</a> . The new release has touched the half million line mark,
	read the exact figures 
	<a href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2003-January/009467.html">
		here
	</a>. We'll be announcing the binary packages soon.	
</p>
<a name="05-01-2003">
	<h2>Jan 05-01-2003: DGEE Demo up and running</h2>
</a>
<p>
	The Dotgnu Webservice container , otherwise known as the 
	Dotgnu execution environment (DGEE) has reached usable
	levels. Chris Smith has hacked up this server which does
	not run inside Apache , but adopts the strategy other
	AppServers like Tomcat has been using. The C# webservice 
	system is functional and uses Apache and 
	<a href="http://www.nfluid.com">Goldwater</a>
	as the network and execution containers respectively. The 
	system is self documenting and includes introspection into 
	the webservices. It currently supports only XmlRpc and is
	only a pre-release.
	Also read more about DGEE 
	<a href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2002-December/009260.html">
	here.
	</a>
</p>
<a name="17-12-2002">
	<h2>Dec 17-12-2002: Mingw32 and Portable.Net</h2>
</a>
<p>
	The Portable.Net platform now works on Win32 without any
	dependencies on the Cygwin wrappers. The build system uses
	the Minimal Gnu For Win32 or Mingw32 libraries to achieve
	this. Read the full announcement  
	<a href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2002-December/009115.html">here</a>.
</p>
<a name="13-12-2002">
	<h2>Dec 13-12-2002: Qt# with Portable.Net</h2>
</a>
<p>
	The <a href="http://qtcsharp.sf.net/">Qt#</a> project has managed to 
	compile its libraries and run the sample programs included with Qt#
	on Portable.Net. Excluding the Xml based bindings generator program , 
	the rest of	Qt# compile and run with ease on Portable.Net. The 
	screenshots have been put up for a peek at Gui programming with 
	Portable.net. Take a look at
	<a href="http://symonds.net/~gopalv82/code/mandelbrot.jpg">mandelbrot</a>
	and 
	<a href="http://symonds.net/~gopalv82/code/pnetscribble.jpg">scribblewindow</a>. 
</p>
<a name="21-11-2002">
	<h2>Nov 21-11-2002: DGEE &amp; Intermodule Messaging.</h2>
</a>
<p>

Chris Smith has brought out a nice specification for the DGEE core module
communication. The good thing about this is that it is not tied down to XML
or any encoding format, but allows arbitary data chunks such as XML, C# 
byte code, HTML form post data etc to be packaged together and sent as a 
single message between the internal components of the VRS/SEE core 
<a href="http://www.nfluid.com/dgee/dgee.html">DGEE</a>.
</p>
<p>
Read the full specification 
<a href="http://www.nfluid.com/dgee/message.html">here</a>. And get a 
proof of concept implementation in C 
<a href="http://www.nfluid.com/download/dgeemsg.tgz">here</a>. 
</p>
<h2>Nov 2-11-2002: Treecc and Ruby output </h2>
<p>
	Thanks to the efforts of Peter Minten (silvernerd) , we  now
	have a Ruby generator for treecc . 
	<a href="http://www.southern-storm.com.au/treecc.html">Treecc</a> 
	is a tool that simplifies construction, manipulation and traversal of
	Abstract Syntax Trees . It was developed for building the Portable.Net
	compiler tools . See announcement 
	<a href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2002-November/008556.html">here</a>.
</p>
<a name="19-10-2002">
	<h2>Oct 19-10-2002: IRC Meeting with Parrot Developers</h2>
</a>
<p>
	The IRC meeting to discuss adding <a href="http://www.parrotcode.org">
	Parrot</a> to the bytecodes supported by Portable.Net was a great 
	success. The Parrot designer was here to discuss the details of 
	generating Parrot from C#. Read all about it 
	<a href="http://dotgnu.org/pipermail/developers/2002-October/008380.html">
	here.
	</a>
</p>
</content>
