<h1>Related Projects</h1>
<h2>Ximian's Mono Project</h2>
About four months after the first public release of
<a href="http://www.southern-storm.com.au/portable_net.html">Portable.NET</a>
on <a href="http://freshmeat.net/">http://freshmeat.net/</a>, Ximian Inc.
announced the competing <a href="http://www.go-mono.com/">Mono</a>
project.  There are some tensions between Mono and Portable.NET
developers, therefore comparisons of features and overall quality are
probably best left to independent journalists.  However it may be helpful to
discuss similarities and differences between the objectives of Portable.NET
and Mono.  (Portable.NET is a major part of the DotGNU project).  In what
follows, the information about Mono is quoted from an interview with
Miguel de Icaza, CTO and co-founder of Ximian Inc, which was
<a href="http://www.fawcette.com/dotnetmag/2002_07/online/netalternatives/default_pf.asp">published in .NET Magazine</a>.
In the introductory paragraph, it is said that the Mono project's
"objective is to include key .NET compliant components, including a C#
compiler, a common language runtime (CLR) just-in-time (JIT) compiler".
The same can be said about Portable.NET, with the difference that
Portable.NET has strong emphasis on having a fast, highly portable
interpreter-based runtime, and less emphasis on JITs, which are
necessarily less portable.  Miguel de Icaza gives more specific
information on what Ximian's specific focus is in his answer to this
question:
<blockquote>
<em><p><strong>.NET Magazine:</strong> Mono is a major undertaking. What is Ximian's interest in coordinating this project, and how does Ximian earn a return on this investment?</p></em>
<p><strong>Miguel de Icaza:</strong> Remember this is an open source project, so we depend on the open source community. The Mono project at Ximian is fairly small. We have five people and one manager dedicated to the entire thing. A lot of it could come from third-party people. What you see here is what has happened with people outside Ximian contributing to the project. Fortunately for us, there are a lot of people interested in the technology who share our preferences for open source. We at Ximian are very focused on the desktop and our main interest is Windows Forms, but a lot of people are interested in ASP.NET. ASP.NET is being half done by developers outside Ximian; and ADO.NET was developed completely outside of Ximian's control, then contributed back to us.</p>
</blockquote>
Here is how this compares to DotGNU Portable.NET:
<ul>
<li>The ultimate goal of Portable.NET is not to generate a Return On Investment
for a specific profit-oriented company, but rather to meet everyone's needs for
a Free Software system that is compatible with .NET</li>
<li>While Portable.NET also welcomes contributions, both from volunteers
and from interested companies (development sponsorships from companies are
also welcome), in Portable.NET no contributor is considered "outside".</li>
<li>While Ximian says that they are very focused on the desktop and mainly
interested in Windows Forms, these areas are important for Portable.NET also.
However from the perspective of Portable.NET, embedded systems are as
important as desktop systems, and webservices are as important as GUI
applications.</li>
<li>For the sake of compatibility with .NET, Portable.NET is also
working on an ASP.NET implementation.  However, Portable.NET is part
of the DotGNU project which is not satisfied with merely re-implementing
what Microsoft has - rather it is time for Free Software to take the
intitiative and gain a position of technological leadership.  For example,
because web browsers are a poor platform for GUIs in general,
we hope that browser-based ASP.NET "web applications" will be rendered obsolete
by PHP as well as an emerging Free Software technology called
<a href="http://www.xwt.org/">XWT</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Links to other related projects</h2>
DotGNU is happy to exchange links with related Free Software projects.
If you have such a project, please contact us.
