<?xml version="1.0"?>
<section name="Projects" prefix="proj">
<menu name="Projects Menu">
	<menuitem name="Home" link="projects.html"/>
	<menuitem name="Portable.NET" link="pnet.html"/>
	<menuitem name="Phpgroupware" link="phpgw.html"/>
	<menuitem name="........." link="projects.html"/>
</menu>
<file name="projects.html">
	<data heading="DotGNU Software Development Projects">
		<!-- the special name __intro__ skips any heading printed -->
		<dataitem heading="__intro__">
			<![CDATA[
				The <a href="index.html">DotGNU vision</a> is so big that for
	practical reasons DotGNU must be organized as a meta-project
	that serves as an umbrella for at least ten to twenty 
	software development projects.
	<p>
	There are two main tracks of development of DotGNU, each of which can
	have any number of DotGNU projects.  New projects can be proposed and
	discussed at any time, as explained on the
	<a href="/proposals/">proposals page</a>.
			]]>
		</dataitem>
		<dataitem heading="DotGNU Platform">
			<![CDATA[
	This webservices platform will support p2p communication between
	multiple webservices servers, so that they can keep their databases in
	synch.
	<ul>
	<li><strong>DotGNU Portable.NET</strong>
	<p>For strategic reasons, the DotGNU Platform must be "downward
    	compatible" to Microsoft's .NET, in the sense that programs
    	("Portable Executables") that have been created for .NET must
    	run on the DotGNU platform.
   	<p>The DotGNU project that is responsible for ensuring this
    	compatibility is the 
    	<a href="http://www.southern-storm.com.au/portable_net.html">DotGNU
    	Portable.NET</a> project led by Rhys Weatherley.
   	<p>This is a high-priority project.
   	<p>
	<li><strong>Support for Java bytecode</strong>
	<p>The invention of the new language C# is a strategic move of
    	Microsoft against the successful Java language.  (It seems that
    	Microsoft wants to fight against everything that is successful
    	and not under the control of Microsoft).  DotGNU wants to support
    	Java and the various languages that can be compiled to Java
    	bytecode, so we need a JVM implementation for the DotGNU Platform.
   	<p>Maybe this will be implemented as part of the pnet package.
   	<p>This isn't actively being worked on yet.
   	<p>
	<li><strong>DotGNU Secure Execution Environment</strong>
	<p>Portable Executables that come in one of the multiple bytecode
    	formats supported by the DotGNU platform will be executed in a
    	<a href="http://savannah.gnu.org/projects/dotgnu-see/">DotGNU
    	Secure Execution Environment.</a> In order to facilitate remote
    	execution, this will probably implemented as a daemon, and there
    	is code for a test daemon called Andromeda which demonstrated how
    	plugins can be bound to the daemon.
   	<p>This is a high-priority project.
   	<p>
	<li><strong>DotGNU Distributed Execution Environment</strong>
	<p>DotGNU's Distributed Execution Environment will be like an
    	operating system for a "distributed computer" consisting of
    	several instances of the "DotGNU Secure Execution Environment"
    	that are running on several computers.  This system must be able
    	to take care of replicating databases across all the parts of this
    	"distributed computer" and propagating updates.
   	<p>This isn't actively being worked on yet.
   	<p>
	</ul>	
			]]>
		</dataitem>
		<dataitem heading="DotGNU Virtual Identities">
			<![CDATA[
	This will be a totally decentralized authentication / personal
	information system that can compete with Microsoft's "Passport"
	system.  This system will eventually implemented as an application
	that runs on the DotGNU platform.  Unlike other applications it makes
	sense to develop this application under the umbrella of the DotGNU
	meta-project, because authentication is also an essential component of
	every operating system.
	<p>
	There are several active projects in this area, but none of them is
	officially part of the GNU project yet.  They're listed on the
	<a href="proposals/active.html">Active Proposals page</a>.
			]]>
		</dataitem>
		<dataitem heading="Supporting Projects">
		<![CDATA[		
		<ul>
		<li><a href="http://dotgnu.org/mailman/listinfo/website">DotGNU website</a>
		<li><a href="http://dotgnu.org/mailman/listinfo/pr">DotGNU PR team</a>
		<li>DotGNU Documentation Project
 		<li>Market Research
		</ul>
		]]>
		</dataitem>
	</data>
</file>
</section>
